Brecht Devleesschauwer (°09/09/1986)

Senior epidemiologist, PhD DVM MVSc MStat

Sciensano, Department of Epidemiology and Public Health

Center for Burden and Risk Assessment—www.cbra.be

brecht.devleesschauwer@sciensano.be | Skype: brecht.devleesschauwer

Rue Juliette Wytsmanstraat 14, 1050 Brussels, Belgium | +32 2 642 5035

Personal statement

Throughout my active research career, the common goal of my research activities has been to quantify the true impact of diseases and health inequalities, and to make model-based evaluations of prevention and control. I have successfully applied these methods to study the health and economic impact of public and animal health threats and to assess cost-effectiveness of intervention strategies. My work has led to new insights in the epidemiology, burden and control of foodborne and zoonotic diseases. I have developed and implemented the computational framework for estimating the global burden of foodborne disease, as an active member of the World Health Organization Foodborne Disease Burden Epidemiology Reference Group (WHO/FERG). These estimates are proving to become instrumental in guiding food safety related decision making processes across the world.

My research activities have led to more than 100 peer-reviewed scientific publications in national and international journals. My scientific expertise in burden assessment, risk assessment and health economics has been recognized through invitations to various national and international expert groups, including the Belgian food safety authority, and EFSA, WHO, and FAO.

Education

• Ph.D. Veterinary Sciences & Ph.D. Public Health, 2010–2015

Ghent University, Merelbeke, Belgium

Université catholique de Louvain, Brussels, Belgium

Dissertation topic: "The Burden of Zoonoses in Nepal"

Promoters: Prof. Dr. P. Dorny, Prof. Dr. N. Speybroeck, Prof. Dr. L. Duchateau

• Doctoral Training Programme, 2010–2015

Doctoral School of Life Sciences and Medicine, Ghent University, Belgium

• M.Sc. Statistics (biometrics), 2011–2014

Katholieke Universiteit Leuven, Louvain, Belgium; Great distinction

Dissertation topic: " $Quantitative\ Microbial\ Risk\ Assessment\ with\ R$ "

Promoters: Prof. Dr. G. Molenberghs, Prof. Dr. C. Faes

• M.Sc. Veterinary Medicine (research & industry), 2007–2010

Ghent University, Merelbeke, Belgium; Greatest distinction

Dissertation topic: "The Epidemiology of Taenia solium in Nepal"

Promoter: Prof. Dr. P. Dorny

• B.Sc. Veterinary Medicine, 2004–2007

Ghent University, Merelbeke, Belgium; Greatest distinction

Employment

• Visiting professor, advanced epidemiology, 10/2018—present Université catholique de Louvain, Brussels, Belgium

• Visiting professor, risk analysis, 04/2018–present Ghent University, Merelbeke, Belgium

• Senior epidemiologist, 04/2016-present Sciensano, Brussels, Belgium

• Visiting professor, health economic evaluations, 10/2016–09/2018 Université catholique de Louvain, Brussels, Belgium

Assistant scientist, global food safety and zoonoses, 06/2015–03/2016
University of Florida, Gainesville, USA

• Post-doctoral researcher, 04/2015 Ghent University, Merelbeke, Belgium

• Contracted technical expert, 09/2013–12/2013, 02/2014–03/2014 World Health Organization, Geneva, Switzerland

Doctoral researcher, 10/2010-03/2015
Ghent University, Merelbeke, Belgium
Université catholique de Louvain, Brussels, Belgium

Mentoring and supervision

36 MSc students8 BSc students

Scientific output

item 6

item 105

Google Scholar metrics: 2648 citations \cdot h-index 23 \cdot i10-index 51